Finding Aid for Elaine Chenevert Donnelly Papers, 1973-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Elaine Chenevert Donnelly Papers 1973-2003, 1985-2001
Donnelly, Elaine Chenevert.
1 linear feet
86998 Aa 2
Anti-ERA activist from Livonia, Michigan. Anti-ERA materials authored and collected by Donnelly as National Media Chair of Phyllis Schlafly's Eagle Forum and founder of the Michigan Stop-ERA Committee, 1974-1983; also materials on the International Women's Year Conferences, 1977-1978; transcript, 1983, of testimony before a Subcommittee of the U.S. House Committee on the Judiciary; publications of Donnelly Media Associates of Livonia, Michigan, 1984; files relating to her interest in issues arising from the participation of women serving in the military, especially her work as executive director of the Center (formerly Coalition) for Military Readiness and her activities as a member of the Presidential Commission on the Assignment of Women in the Armed Forces; and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Elaine Donnelly (donor no. 7254 ) beginning in 1985. Periodic additions have been received.
The collection is open to research.
Elaine Donnelly was an anti-ERA activist from Livonia, Michigan. She also served on the Presidential Commission on the Assignment of Women in the Armed Forces in the 1990s.
The Donnelly collection (1 linear foot)inches contains a wide variety of materials relating to her political activity. The collection has been arranged into two series: Topical and Women in the Military. The Subject File is arranged alphabetically by topic, and composed of clippings, correspondence, articles, press releases, newsletters, brochures, and schedules. There are four folders dealing with Donnelly's anti-ERA efforts (1973-1986). There is here material concerning her endorsement of political candidates, including Ronald Reagan (1980, 1984), Jack Kemp (1986-1988), and Richard Chrysler (1986). The Women in the Military series documents her work as executive director of the Center (formerly Coalition) for Military Readiness and her activities as a member of the Presidential Commission on the Assignment of Women in the Armed Forces.
Subjects:
Chenevert, Basil J.; Insurance, Health--United States.; International Women's Year, 1975.; Michigan Stop-ERA Committee.; Schlafly, Phyllis.; Women's rights--United States.; Donnelly, Elaine Chenevert.; Women in politics--Michigan--Livonia.; United States--Armed Forces--Women.; United States. Presidential Commission on the Assignment of Women in the Armed Forces.; Women in combat--Government policy--United States.; Center for Military Readiness.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
National Women's Conference (1st: 1977: Houston, Tex.); Women.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical
  - Donnelly Family Tree 1981, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Anti-ERA Materials
    - General (Box 1)
    - Michigan Stop ERA Committee 1975, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Clippings from the Stop ERA Campaign 1973, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Vermont State ERA 1986 (Box 1)
  - Reagan Campaign 1980, 1984 (Box 1)
  - 1986-1988 Presidential Race, Jack Kemp (Box 1)
  - Michigan Governor's Race, Richard Chrysler 1986 (Box 1)
  - Comparable Worth 1984 (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Convention 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General 1979-1986 (Box 1)
    - Doug Gamble 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - FCC Fairness Doctrine 1984 (Box 1)
  - IWY Convention 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Media Consultant 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - National Media Chairman 1979 (Box 1)
  - Republican Issues Committee 1987 (Box 1)
  - SDI (Star Wars) Geneva Summit Material 1983-1986 (Box 1)
  - Testimony for the Subcommittee of U.S. House Committee on the Judiciary 1983 (Box 1)
  - Unisex Insurance 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Basil Chenevert and catastrophic health coverage 1983-1988 (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    (mainly from the International Women's Year Conference in Houston, Texas in 1977, including platform and auditorium photos)
  - Newspaper Articles 1973-1985 (Box 1)
- Women in the Military
  - DACOWITS (Defense Advisory Committee on Women in the Services 1985 (Box 1)
  - Coalition for Military Readiness, Memos and Bulletins (Box 1)
  - Center for Military Readiness
    - Newsletter: V.I.P. Notes, 1994-1997, 2 folders (Box 1)
      (subsequent issues entitled CMR Notes cataloged and shelved separately)
    - News Releases 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - CMR Reports 1993-2003 (Box 1)
    - VIP Notes 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Prospects for 1992, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Double Standards in Naval Aviation 1995 (Box 1)
    - Case for Financial Investment and Support 1999 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Commission on the Assignment of Women in the Armed Forces
    - Report Task Force 1988 (Box 1)
    - Reports from Panels 1 and 3 1992 (Box 1)
    - Alternative Views 1992 (Box 1)
    - Definition of Combat (Box 1)
    - Desert Storm 1992 (Box 1)
    - Prisoner's of War 1992 (Box 1)
    - Other Countries (Box 1)
    - Trip Reports
      - Naval Academy 1992 (Box 1)
      - Parris Island Ft. Brag 1992 (Box 1)
      - Nellis/Navy 1992 (Box 1)
      - U.S.S. JFK 1992 (Box 1)
      - West Point 1992 (Box 1)
      - McDill/Special Forces 1992 (Box 1)
      - Quantico 1992 (Box 1)
      - Norfolk Naval Station 1992 (Box 1)
      - Defense Civil Institute of Environmental Medicine, Toronto, Canada 1992 (Box 1)
  - Politics and the Pentagon: The Role of Women in the Military by Elaine Donnelly 1991 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings
    - 1990-1991 (Box 1)
    - 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 1)